Guide to the Jim Brown Papers, 1945-1959 and undated
The John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Jim Brown papers 1945-1959 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Brown, Jim
2.4 Linear Feet 250 Items
R.C. Jim Brown served as copy group head of Batten, Barton, Durstine & Osborne (BBDO) during the years 1945-1962.
The Jim Brown Papers contain materials representing the years of Brown's employment with BBDO. The collection consists of a scrapbook of advertising proofs and a series of proposals relating to BBDO clients' sponsorship of television specials. Included in the scrapbook are proofs for publication in trade magazines, newspapers, movie posters, and comic books, with most of the materials dating from 1945-1946. Companies and products represented include Royal Crown Cola (Cott Beverages), Ethyl Cleaner (Ethyl Corporation), Raleigh Cigarettes, Kool Cigarettes, Continental Can Company and the American Broadcasting Company. The set of proposals date from 1955-1959 and includes BBDO strategies for product placement in advertisements and in the television programs, as well as rate schedules for various marketing tactics. Companies represented include Du Pont, Westclox, Bristol-Myers, General Electric Company and Campbell Soup Company. Television programs to be sponsored include Lassie, The Donna Reed Show, Playhouse 90, and Wonderful Town.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Jim Brown Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2000.
Biographical Note
R.C. "Jim" Brown was born on 15 April 1912 in Yelverton, OH. He received his B.A. in 1934 from the University of Dayton, where he was president of the Dayton Advertising Club and a member of the fraternity Chi Alpha Phi. On 21 November 1936 he married Ruth Carothers Johnson. He eventually served as copy group head for Batten, Barton, Durstine & Osborn (BBDO), and later as creative director for Bermingham, Castleman & Pierce, Inc., both in New York City. During 1940-1941, he served as president of the Greater Dayton Advertising Association, as a trustee for New York's Ohio Society, as chairman of the New York Civil War Round Table Tour. He also sponsored the Madison Avenue Advertising Agency, and was the recipient of the Public Relations Society of America's Silver Anvil Award. He died on 26 July 1999.
Collection Overview
The Jim Brown Papers contain materials representing the years of Brown's employment with BBDO. The collection consists of a scrapbook of advertising proofs and a series of proposals relating to BBDO clients' sponsorship of television specials. Included in the scrapbook are proofs for publication in trade magazines, newspapers, movie posters, and comic books, with most of the materials dating from 1945-1946. Companies and products represented include Royal Crown Cola (Cott Beverages), Ethyl Cleaner (Ethyl Corporation), Raleigh Cigarettes, Kool Cigarettes, Continental Can Company and the American Broadcasting Company. The set of proposals date from 1955-1959 and includes BBDO strategies for product placement in advertisements and in the television programs, as well as rate schedules for various marketing tactics. Companies represented include Du Pont, Westclox, Bristol-Myers, General Electric Company and Campbell Soup Company. Television programs to be sponsored include Lassie, The Donna Reed Show, Playhouse 90, and Wonderful Town.
The collection is organized into two sections: a set of proposals related to company marketing through television programs, and a scrapbook of advertising proofs.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Brown, Jim, 1912-1999
Batten, Barton, Durstine & Osborn, Inc
E.I. du Pont de Nemours & Company
Westclox (Firm)
Bristol-Myers Company
General Electric Company
Campbell Soup Company
Cott Beverages Limited
Ethyl Corporation
Brown & Williamson
Continental Can Company
American Broadcasting Company
Advertising agencies
Advertising agencies -- United States
Radio advertising
Advertising -- Television programs
Television advertising
Product placement in mass media -- United States -- History
Proofs
Scrapbook
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Related Material
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections of J. Walter Thompson Company Archives: Colin Dawkins Papers; Edgar Hatcher Papers. Other related materials may be found in: Anthony Weir Papers; John E. Brennan Outdoor Advertising Survey Reports; Judith Hennessee Papers; Roy Lightner Collection Of Antique Advertisements; John Benjamin Harris Papers; Liggett and Myers Tobacco Company Records; Garrett Orr Papers; Brouillard Communications, Inc., Vertical Files.
- Proposals, 1955-1959, 1 Box
  The proposals date from 1955 to 1959 and were compiled by members of BBDO for various client companies looking to sponsor television broadcasts of special programs. Companies include Westclox, General Electric, Du Pont, Campbell Soup Company, and Bristol-Myers. Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Plan for publicity promotion station merchandising of Wonderful Town sponsored by Westclox, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Proposed promotion plan for Lassie sponsored by Campbell Soup Company, 1958-1959
  - Proposed publicity promotion plan for The Donna Reed Show sponsored by Campbell Soup Company, 2 copies, 1958-1959
  - Recommended audience promotion plan for the General Electric Theater, 1955-1956
  - Recommended publicity promotion plan for Playhouse 90 sponsored by Bristol-Myers, 1956
  - Total exploitation publicity promotion plan for Du Pont Presents sponsored by E.I. Du Pont De Nemours & Co., 1957
- Scrapbook, 1945-1946, 1958 and undated, 1 Box
  Contains advertising proofs for publication in newspapers, trade magazines, movie posters and comic books. Companies and products represented include Royal Crown Cola, Ethyl Cleaner, Raleigh Cigarettes, Kool Cigarettes, Continental Can Company, and the American Broadcasting Company. Original scrapbook order was preserved, and original folder titles were used.
  - Royal Crown Cola, 1945-1946 (Box 2)
    - Life color pages
    - Life half pages
    - Movie books
    - Good Housekeeping
    - Negro
    - Adventure [comics]
    - Newspaper campaigns
    - Trade publications
    - Posters, miscellaneous
  - Ethyl Cleaner, 1946
    - Newspaper campaigns
    - Cartoons, cartoon strips
    - Proof for Woman's Day, other trade publications
  - Raleigh Cigarettes, Kool Cigarettes, 1945
  - Continental Can Company, 1945-1946
  - American Broadcasting Company, 1945